So, um, what I'd like to do today is chat with you about the full cycle of a deep learning project.
And as I promised in the first lecture, rather than me talking at you for an hour and 20 minutes or whatever,
um, we'd love for this to be much more interactive.
And so what I'm going to do is illustrate this as an example,
but also ask you a bunch of questions along the way about what you would do
if you are the one working on the project that I'm going to use as an illustrative example.
Okay, so plan for this to be quite interactive and please interrupt any time and ask questions
since I think that's why, uh, you know, I want to do this in person here at Stanford.
Um, so one of the reasons why developing machine learning or deep learning
or other types of AI projects, including AI projects using large language models
or agency guide workflows or whatever, is that AI projects are different than traditional software engineering projects.
So one of the biggest difference between AI projects of the many different flavors,
civilized learning, LMBase, um, you know, generative AI base is that
in traditional software projects, you write code and you control your code, right?
Write whatever code you want, compile it, your code does what you tell it to.
But AI projects, you know, involve both code as well as data that you train your algorithm on
and you almost never know what strange and wonderful things there are in your data.
For example, if you're working on a face recognition application,
that's a running example I'm going to use today, then as you're just getting started on the project,
you actually, it's really difficult to know in advance what you find in the data.
Is the lighting of the faces good? Do you struggle with people with very long hair or people with short hair?
Do people making weird facial expressions make your system struggle?
Do people wearing glasses make your system struggle?
So data is so rich that a lot of time you can't predict in advance what your AI system is going to do,
not because you don't control the code.
So you can write whatever new network or whatever code you want, but you don't know what's in the data.
And this is why, unlike traditional software engineering, machine learning development is a much more iterative process
where you just have to build something, see how it works, and then through a process,
discover, almost discover what is in the data and therefore what you should be doing
to change your code to make your overall system perform.
This is also true, not just for, this is true not just for deep learning based systems,
this is also true for modern large language models.
If there's been a lot of hype buzz about how LLMs, large language models, are hard to control,
I think there's a lot of excessive hype about that, you know, kind of fear-mongering, there's a little bit of that.
But one of the reasons why none of us know in advance what LLMs do is because it was trained on a lot of data,
more data than any human could possibly look at, and we just don't know, you know,
what precision, what is in all that data that the app was trained on.
And so because we don't know the data, we can't really look at all the massive tens of trillions of tokens of data was trained on.
It's hard to know exactly how a large language model will perform,
which is why building agent-based applications or building large language models based applications is also very empirical or very experimental,
meaning you just have to build something, then see where it goes well,
see where it goes poorly, and then use that to fix problems.
And that's how you drive progress.
That make sense?
So because you control your code, but you don't really know, it's hard to control the data.
And this is true, both for the data you have stored in your hard disk.
You're going to have, I don't know, terabytes of data stored in a hard disk.
I don't really know what's in my hard disk.
And the thing you really don't control is what data the world will give you in the future.
So we deploy a system in the world, safe face recognition, which we should talk about.
People wear a thick, heavy scarf that covers part of their face when it's winter.
You just don't know.
There are all these things in data that will surprise you.
And if you don't even control your past data that's already in your hard disk, you certainly can't control your future data.
So it turns out that a lot of machine learning classes talk about building models, right?
And you learn a lot from the online videos about how to build powerful deep learning models.
But it turns out that building the overall machine learning system or deep learning system has a lot more work than just training models.
But if you look at a lot of courses, there's actually a very strong focus on modeling because I think that's what academia has focused on.
We can train models, evaluate models, publish papers on models.
And so you find that a lot of courses focus on training a good deep learning model.
And that is absolutely important.
But because we know how to evaluate models, different research groups can benchmark different models.
So there's a lot of academic research work on that that's reflecting a lot of courses.
But this is just a small part of what you need to do if you want to build an effective deep learning system.
And what I want to do today is go outside the small box of models to give you a broader view of what it feels like to develop a deep learning or a machine learning system.
And this is what it often says.
This is what building a deep learning system would be like, which is first.
Specify the problem, figure out what we're actually working on.
The running example I want to use today will be to build a face recognition system or face rec system for security, for deciding when to unlock a door.
And I know Kian talked about some face recognition, which I believe face rec architectures last week as well.
But a specific application I want to talk about is something I've worked on.
Actually, I built one of the commercial systems for this.
If this is a door and this is, well, you or a friend or maybe someone that you don't want to let in approaching, if you have a low camera, sorry, bad drawing,
take a picture of whoever's approaching the door and decide whether or not to unlock the door.
So face recognition to decide who's authorized to enter, like a restricted location, like a corporate office building or your house or whatever.
And actually, one common use case that one of my teams built was key card, swipe key cards.
So sometimes key cards get stolen.
And so one of the systems we deployed, you know, fairly large office complexes was if you swipe a key card, we also just take a picture,
student just called it to make sure that the key card is held by the person whose face is shown on the key card.
So it makes it harder for someone to steal a key card to gain unauthorized access to the office complex.
So I'm going to use this as the motivating example for today.
And after specifying a problem, typical process is then sometimes the open source model can download.
But let's say for today that the open source models aren't good enough.
You want to train your own model.
The simple process we get data, you know, design a model, train a model.
And then we will iterate through these steps a bunch of times until the model looks like it's performing well enough.
And then after that, we have to deploy it and maintain the model.
OK, so I'm going to talk a bunch about multiple of these steps today because I want you to come away with a feel for
when you're working on a real machine learning application, what the important steps you will face on.
And so as I alluded, machine learning development is very iterative process.
So for these three steps, we often drive a rapid development loop where we design the model, train it,
analyze the results, and then maybe design or update the model, the data or something,
and iterate around this loop many times before you are satisfied.
And all right, just one more detail.
It turns out that for face recognition, the very common architecture which you learn in detail about later in the online videos
is a neural network called a Siamese network.
And what that does is a neural network that takes as input two pictures,
and two pictures get fed to a neural network or a deep learning algorithm.
And it's a job of the deep learning algorithm to tell us are these two pictures the same person or different persons?
Because if you're trying to set this system safe for your house,
and maybe you have a few family members or roommates you want to let in,
then it would be quite annoying if they retrained a neural network for every single home.
So the most common way to do face recognition is of a neural network that inputs two pictures,
and the job of the neural network is to tell me are these two pictures the same person?
And then the way you set up the system is to input a few registration pictures.
So take a picture of yourself, take a picture of your roommate,
take a picture of any family members you want to have access.
So then when someone comes, you can quickly check if the person that just showed up
is one of the people that's authorized, and then let them in.
And then the corporate key card swipe example is someone swipes a card,
and my card says this is Andrew's card,
then I'll quickly pull up my registration picture to double check if I am,
if I seem to be the same person as the Andrew that was registered.
So this is a typical neural network architecture.
All right, so I have a question for you.
One thing I'd like to do today is walk you through a number of scenarios
and invite you to think about what decision you would make
if you are the CTO of a startup building these technologies, right?
So my question for you is, if you are the CTO of a startup building
the next phase recognition system,
and if your lawyers have said you aren't allowed to download data from the internet,
right, so let's not download data from the internet for this application,
how would you go about getting data to train the system?
So what you need is a bunch of pictures of people, right,
to train a neural network to say, you know, are they the same person or not?
So maybe take a few minutes to think about it,
and then I'll see if you can raise hands and give some answers.
And one specific question I have as well is,
how long would you take to collect data before you start training a model?
Right, so I think, well, you need to get data,
we've designed a model, I guess, and then you need to train a model.
So what does the timeline look for you?
We specify the problem, you know, we design the model,
how many hours or days or weeks we just spend to get data and how,
before you start running, you know, gradient descent.
I see your hand up.
Oh, sure, go ahead.
Let me leave it a bit more open-ended.
Say you just graduated from Stanford,
and your CTO of a three-person startup building this thing,
that eventually, hopefully, you sell all around the world,
but your goal is to just get started with the three of you working all of,
you know, Palo Alto, California,
and do it as your real self, right, with the resources that you have.
All right, anyone want to venture an answer?
How would you get data to train the neural network?
Go for it.
Yeah, cool, video streaming service.
By video streaming service, you're thinking like, you know, Netflix and Hulu,
or are you thinking like security videos?
Oh, like Zoom.
Oh, I see, I see, cool.
I see, cool, cool, right, cool.
All right, video streaming service.
How long do you think it will take to do that?
Cool, all right, cool, thank you.
All right, creative idea.
Any idea what it is?
How would you go about and get data?
Go ahead.
Yeah, cool, awesome.
All right, stick a camera there.
Let people, you know, opt in, right, to get the picture taken.
Cool.
I think I saw a hand up.
Go for it.
Oh, sorry.
I see, cool.
How would you get users?
I see, cool, right.
Yeah, by your own people, you can like grab some friends and also they'll give you that LinkedIn photo,
give you some pictures from the camera roll.
Yeah, cool, I like that.
That's fast.
I like that.
Any other ideas?
Oh, good.
I see, interesting.
Yeah, I'll stand for to send an email.
Cool.
But I love Stanford.
Stanford is a wonderful institution.
That's going to take a while.
Really creative idea.
I like the creative ideas.
So let me share with you one guiding principle for how I would encourage you to approach this problem of data collection.
I appreciate all the creative ideas, actually.
One of the frameworks I often use to decide how I collect data is speed.
Because I find that, especially when building a startup, in my opinion,
one of the strongest predictors for whether a startup will succeed and also whether a small innovative project in a large corporation,
it could be a giant corporation, but a team of three working on a small innovative project in a big company,
I find that one of the biggest predictors for the chance of success is just the speed of execution.
It's just speed of getting stuff done.
And so when I'm sitting with a team and brainstorming different tactics,
I will gravitate toward the tactics that let me get the data set very quickly.
And quickly usually means, you know, like one or two days,
even if it ends up with an inferior, smaller, lower quality data sets or whatever.
Because I don't really know what problems I'll see in my data.
And the quicker I can, you know, get the data set, train a model, see where it goes wrong,
the quicker I can then discover what's wrong with my data and fix it.
True story, chatting with a CEO that told me he actually had spent I think it was over $100 million,
definitely more than $10 million, spent a lot of money buying a company for its data.
And then she actually said, hey, Andrew, I've spent all this money to get all this data.
You know, can you help me figure out how to monetize this, how to make money off of this?
And I kind of looked at it and said, boy, I kind of wish I hadn't done that.
And what I find is that the value of data is just so difficult to know in advance.
What's important and what's not important about data.
So for a lot of these tactics, for example, I think student ID is an interesting one.
But, you know, our student ID photos weird in some way, right?
Or are they too expressionless or people smiling too much in student IDs?
I actually have no idea.
Actually, my Stanford ID, I look really weird in my Stanford ID.
Or and I think you and I actually like the idea of sticking a camera
and just letting people come up and opt in and take a picture if you can do it quickly.
And I think in a big company or even in a small startup, if you know,
it's important to respect user privacy or individual privacy.
But if you can stick a camera in some place, you know, that doesn't kind of,
what's the word, invade people's privacy,
that don't want to be any part of this, but let people opt in,
take the pictures of permission.
If you can do that in days, I find that to be valuable.
One other thing I found for quite a few of my projects,
I found that Stanford students, our community here is pretty cosmopolitan.
We're people from all around the world.
We're not fully representative of the world's distribution of people,
but we actually do have people from all around the world.
A lot of Stanford people are actually very nice.
So one thing I've done multiple times is when I need to collect data,
we'll go to places on campus with high foot traffic.
It turns out cafeteria is a very high foot traffic.
And we just ask people, hey, work on the project.
Can I get a sample of your voice?
Can I take a picture of you?
Kind of with really informed concern.
Tell people, is it okay if I do this?
I've been delighted at how collaborative Stanford students are.
And I find that one thing I've often done is gone to my teams
and said, we have two days to collect data.
It's like, whatever.
It's 11.52 a.m. now.
Let's figure out what we can do by, what day is it? Tuesday.
Let's figure out what we can do by Thursday, 11.52 a.m.
So this gives us 48 hours, and let's brainstorm.
How can we collect data?
And it's fine that the data isn't all there,
fine that the data is low quality,
but that velocity lets us more quickly trade a model,
figure out what's wrong with the data,
and then jigger or retweak how we collect data.
So I find that some teams will ask,
how can we collect the data we need?
And then ask, how long would that take?
That usually leads to much slower execution.
I instead tend to go to my teams and say,
we have two days or one day or maybe a week, right,
some short time span like that,
and say, what's the most creative, you know,
respectful, responsible, but creative way you can use
to collect data in a short time span.
And one of the ways to think about that too is
trading a model takes, I don't know,
let's say it takes two days.
Maybe I should take more like one day, right?
If you can trade a model in a couple of days,
then I would not spend, you know, like whatever, right,
two months to find data to trade a model,
because then this becomes a huge bottleneck.
Because you can trade a model relatively quickly,
let's take a commensurate amount of time
to design a model or design the data as trade a model.
And depending on how long it takes to trade a model,
sometimes trade a model, you know,
it needs to run overnight.
I actually see teams sometimes take one day
iteration loops around this.
The fast-moving teams I work with,
we often go around this loop once per day
for the smaller models.
If we're trading a large air foundation model,
sometimes trading a model takes weeks or even months,
then the process can be different.
If your model run is going to be, you know,
two months, then yeah, maybe it makes sense
to spend, you know, a couple months
to get the data really right.
If you have a large air foundation,
you could train that overnight,
or actually in a couple hours quite easily.
So it makes sense not to spend massive amounts of time
before you go in to train the model.
Does that make sense?
And because, oh, the word empirical
means experimental, right?
Sorry, I've used the word a few times today.
And I think we say that machine learning
is a very empirical process,
we have to do it, see what happens,
and decide what to do next.
I know that sometimes others have criticized our field
as like, we never know what we're doing,
we just try stuff and see what works.
And, you know, there's a little bit of truth to that.
I think understanding neural networks,
hyperparameters, architecture,
that is really valuable,
so we don't just try stuff at random.
But because we don't know what's in the data,
we do try a lot of things,
and then drive a disparate process,
understand what works and what doesn't,
and then use that to navigate forward.
Does that make sense?
And then I'll just say there's one exception
to the advice I'm giving here,
which is if you're working on a project
that you have worked on many times before,
so, you know, whatever,
I've built a bunch of face recognition systems.
So I kind of have a sense from previous experience
and from reading research papers
that certain things I know are just not going to work
if I have, you know, a hundred images, right?
So there's some face recognition systems I know
I probably need at least 50,000 images
before they'll have any hope of working.
So because of that prior experience,
having gone through that loop a lot,
I now have a basis to say,
okay, I do need 50,000 images,
then I might invest upfront
and put more effort upfront
to get those 50,000 images.
But I think for most applications you work on
for the first time,
if you don't have academic literature
to justify certain larger data investments,
or if you don't have prior experience yourself,
then I would focus on the speed
of iterating around this loop.
Make sense?
All right.
And to relate this to
large language models-based applications as well,
a lot of us, a lot of you are probably,
well, you may be building applications
like prompting OMS and calling an API, right?
Like an OpenAI or Anthropic or Gemini
or Metalarmor or whatever API
to get things back from OMS.
One of the reasons that too
is a very experimental,
a very iterative empirical process
is because when you write an OMS prompt,
you don't really know in advance
how it's going to do
because it was trained on data
that none of us have really looked at.
And that too is why,
instead of theorizing for a long time
about what prompt to use in OMS,
you know, just try it out.
And then just by doing that,
you then see the problems
and then your focus can be on fixing the problems.
Make sense?
And in fact,
there's a lot of discussion on responsible AI,
how to make sure AI systems are safe
or they don't have kind of unforeseen circumstances.
And because a lot of the theorizing,
you know, you can only theorize so much,
I find that if you want to build
safe, responsible AI systems,
one of the best ways to do that
is to just build it
and then experiment with it
in a sandbox environment.
Just don't let it out in the world
until you've tested it rigorously,
but just go build something
and then, you know, test it,
probe it in the safety of your own laptop, right?
Don't let it end to innocent users
and have some weird impact on innocent third parties.
But there's only by building it
and then probing it
that you can figure out where can it go wrong,
where it will say inappropriate things,
where it would respond inappropriately
to certain user queries
and then that tells you
where the problems are
when you work on that decision.
Okay?
All right, yeah, question?
Oh, sorry, is that you?
So like, when you do some work,
like when you do analytics,
how do you complete that?
Yeah, right.
Great question.
So when you analyze something
that's wrong with your model,
how do you use that
to take the next step forward, right?
That's a big topic
that we'll talk at length
multiple times in some of the videos
and also in some future lessons,
but maybe long story short,
one of the things you could do
is change your neural network architecture.
You may realize that
maybe the assignment sample isn't working
or read the literature to change your architecture.
The other thing you can often do
is change your data.
So data-centric AI is a discipline
of systematically entering your data
to build a successful AI system.
And it turns out
that you build a face recognition system.
Let's say, I like your hat,
snap the hat, let's go.
But let's say hypothetically
that you find that the system
really struggles recognizing people
that are wearing hats.
Then you may say, all right,
I need to get more data
with people wearing hats, right?
And so it's often that
looking at what goes wrong,
which we call error analysis,
that then gives you the insight
to say, oh, it works well
on these types of data
or these types of users,
but the struggles of these types of users
and those data,
so can I fix my data
or get more data
just on the subset of cases it struggles with?
And that's a very common motion.
That's a very common process
for then driving the performance of the system.
And this is also why
blindly going out to grab more data
willy-nilly,
that's often not a good strategy
because it's just too much data you get.
Do I want more data
with people with long hair
or short hair
or people with facial hair,
sorry, too much hair,
too many hair examples,
or do I want people
with wearing a scarf,
covering part of the face
or people that wear glasses,
or people that don't wear glasses,
or people that are slightly turned away.
There's just so many different types of data
you could invest effort to get more of
that until you build a system,
see where it goes well,
see where it goes poorly,
it's really difficult to decide
where to get more data
and just get more data
of everything under the sun.
That's very slow and expensive.
And I think part of the hype
about the value of data
has led people to have sometimes
overly simplistic view of data, right?
Yes, of course I want more data,
but just grabbing more data
of all types of data
is a very inefficient,
very expensive way
to improve my system.
And even if you look at the way
that frontier models are trained right now,
it's not a game
of just grabbing more data
of anything under the sun.
It is identifying the subcategories
where it's valuable
to invest to get high quality data,
which is why if you look at them,
it turns out in AI,
there are two clear buckets
of value in LLMs, right?
There's the general
answering people's questions.
I think, you know,
OpenAI is actually
doing really well there.
Gemini, Anthropic have momentum,
but there's the general
answering general questions.
And then one of the verticals
is really valuable
is AI for coding the system.
So I think, you know,
Claude has been ahead for a while,
but OpenAI, you know,
I don't know,
Gemini 2.5 Pro,
some of the models
are making really good
progress in coding as well.
And if you look at the team,
look at the work
that the frontier teams
are doing to improve coding,
building iterative agentic
workflows is part of it,
but also finding clever ways
to come up with coding-related data
is also part of it.
And if you want your alum
to do better in coding,
you don't grab data
with low quality,
random internet chat,
social media,
whatever data, right?
But instead,
having high quality coding
related data
is how you can have
a focused effort
to improve your alum's ability
to code.
So a lot of these things
are actually, yeah,
I feel like more data is better.
That is absolutely true,
but it's also
an overly simplistic thing.
Data is not monolithic.
There are subcategories of data,
and having a view on
what piece of data
to really invest in
getting a lot more of,
that's really important
to being efficient
in how you improve
your system performance.
That make sense?
All right,
we'll talk more about
error analysis in this data.
Any other questions?
Cool.
Yeah, go for it.
Yeah, right.
So as you collect data,
the quality of data
matters a lot too,
which is why,
and I think data quality
is tricky, I think.
When building an application
for the first time,
I would still focus on speed
and collecting some data quickly,
but as you then analyze
where your system is going,
why and what it's doing poorly,
you often find that
the quality of data
really matters.
So, I'll talk about this now later.
I'll come back,
so let's see,
let's go there.
All right, let me talk about LM1.
There's a lot of low-quality
random chat on the internet
that's not that useful
for training LMs.
But I think, you know,
this is actually now well-known
that if you can legally access
very high-quality written,
authored articles or books,
they're highly edited,
very insightful,
but that's very high-quality
data for training LMs.
And I'll give an example later as well
for face recognition.
It turns out that, you know,
blurry images, right,
would be low-quality,
then sharp and focused images,
assuming that's representative
of how you want to recognize
people's faces.
So that really matters as well.
All right, anything else?
Cool.
All right.
Oh, yeah, go for it.
Yeah, so, right,
just repeat for Mike.
How important is it
that the data you collect
is similar to the distribution
of things you want to work on?
I think it's important,
but not as important
as most people might think.
So, it turns out that
it turns out one of the reasons
neural networks have been so effective
is because when you build
a very large neural network,
you can throw all sorts of data into it,
including data that is, you know,
not perfectly tuned
to your test set distribution,
and it often doesn't hurt
so long as your network is big enough.
So, you raise the example,
whether we have it identify
two identical objects, right?
If it's generic objects,
like, I don't know,
water bottles and markers,
maybe that's too far afield,
but if we were to use, let's say,
you know, simulated cartoonish characters,
right, that look really different
than real humans,
my guess is it probably won't hurt at all,
and it may even help a little bit.
And so, throwing in a lot of data,
if we train a large neural network
with a lot of capacity
to absorb even some slightly irrelevant data,
it usually doesn't hurt
and might even help a little bit,
but how much it helps
is another empirical question
that will be problem dependent,
and we often just have to try it out.
But I think maybe, you know,
like, in the past,
people used to have an obsession
that the data you train on
has to come from exactly the same distribution
as the solution you test on.
That used to be how machining was done,
I don't know, like, 10, 15 years ago.
That's really not true today anymore.
I think we're very comfortable.
And I think when neural networks
were much smaller,
where you could train very small models,
there was a sense that you didn't want
to distract the neural network
with irrelevant data, right?
Because computer was expensive,
with few parameters,
and you're distracted on irrelevant stuff,
maybe it gets less good
at the core tasks you really care about.
But if you can train it bigger
than a neural network,
which is getting easier and easier these days,
then it's become much more okay
to toss in some data
that hopefully isn't incorrect data.
I think incorrect data is a problem,
but just irrelevant examples
hurts much less,
because big neural networks
is like a human brain, right?
You know, I don't know.
The fact that, whatever,
the fact that I learned to play the piano,
you know, probably doesn't make me worse at AI, right?
Because hopefully my brain is big enough
to learn to play the piano
and learn some self-able AI.
And I think as neural networks get big enough,
they can learn some other irrelevant things
and also do well
with the core tasks you really care about.
But this is less true when, you know,
if my brain was really small,
then I don't think any of you
are fans of Sherlock Holmes,
but I think Sherlock Holmes had an attic theory
that your brain has only so much capacity,
so you've got to forget some stuff
to learn new stuff.
But when you train very large neural networks,
that's much less true.
Cool.
All right, thank you for all the questions.
So what I want to do is just
keep going through this flow, right?
So we talked about your data design model,
trainer model.
We'll talk a lot more about error analysis
later this quarter of how to figure out
where your algorithm is still subpar
and where to focus efforts to improve it.
But what I want to do is
give you a sense of deployment, right?
So when you have trained a model,
it's often a bunch of software engineering work
to then maybe take your model
hosting the cloud on the local server
and have it run inference, right?
It's a very common architecture
for deploying machine learning model
will be that you have a neural network
as a piece of software.
You deploy it maybe on the cloud hosted service
so that your software can accept a picture
or set two pictures and it will reply back,
you know, do I unlock the door or not?
Or is this the same person or not?
So there's a bunch of software engineering work
that needs to be done.
But in practical deployment settings,
I'll actually tell you,
it turns out that if you're building
a practical face recognition system,
you probably find that if you are trying
to unlock a door, you know,
to a corporate campus,
it's too expensive or too slow
to stream video 24-7 to cloud
to classify every frame at 30 frames per second
to see if, you know,
there's a person that you should unlock the door for.
So in practical face recognition systems,
what we end up doing,
actually, let's take the example
of someone walk up to the door,
to your home, to your door at home,
and you want to see if there's someone there
you should unlock the door for, right?
So a lot of systems will actually
have an image from the camera
and then try to build a system.
All right.
So what we have so far, right,
is a system that takes a simple image
and maybe a reference image.
A neural network says,
do I unlock the door or not?
But it turns out that if streaming video
is too expensive,
classifying every frame is too expensive,
we'll often end up with a system like this.
I'm going to...
Well, the VAD sense of visual activity detection.
And what this does is a usually low-cost,
low-power, inexpensive computer job to run
to just very quickly maybe try to figure out
is there a human face there.
Because it turns out, actually,
if you're building something,
unlock your front door, you know,
to you and your friends.
If you look up my front door and my house,
like, it's pretty boring, you know.
There's a wall,
but we see it all over the street,
but nothing moves most of the time.
So this very obviously,
almost all of the time is very obvious
that there's no one outside my front door
trying to be let in,
and it'd be very wasteful to stream all that video
to the internet for classification, right?
So visual activity detection is usually
a low-cost, low-power system
to just very quickly decide,
should I do the work of sending this
to the larger face recognition system
neural network that may be hosted on the cloud
to have it do the much more computationally expensive work
to decide, you know, zero or one,
do I unlock the door or not.
Okay?
So this type of optimization
in order to make the system computationally feasible
to deploy is fairly common,
and I'm going to give you two options
for how to implement VAD,
and I'm going to ask you to reflect on them
and then tell me which one you would pick to get started.
Okay?
So option one is a non-machine learning-based method,
which is see if the number of pixels changed
is greater than some threshold epsilon, right?
So if the camera is stationary,
maybe looking at a wall,
most of the time the pixels barely change
because, you know, it's just a wall,
and so you can write a little bit of code
using, you know, some image library
like PIL, Python Imaging Library,
or some simple, write a few lines of code
to just say, has the number of pixels
whose RGB values have changed more than some threshold
has more than, you know, 10% of the pixels changed
compared to what it looked like a second ago
in order to see if there's anything
in front of your camera
to even decide to pass this to a more high part neural network.
Okay?
Option two would be to train a small neural network.
So face recognition is a pretty complex task.
You have to look at multiple cues in the face,
look at the eyes, look at the mouth, look at the, you know,
so that piece of relatively large neural network.
But just taking a quick glance to see
is there even a human in front of my door?
That's a much simpler task.
So option two would be to train a very small,
very low-power, very lightweight neural network
to just very quickly tell you,
do you think there's a human there?
And then use this train model to decide,
is it worth passing on to a much more powerful
neural network running in the cloud
with a lot more resources
to make the final determination.
Okay?
So if you are the, again, CTO
or a three-person software building this,
how would you, how would you start?
We'll give everyone a few seconds to reflect on this now.
Get people's thoughts.
Go for it.
All right, cool.
All right, just repeating my mic.
So problem-dependent depends on whether you're on the street
with a lot of people walking past,
maybe concern other algorithms.
They're even cheaper than small neural network.
Cool.
Yeah, cool.
Great.
So use option one in the short term
and then maybe replace that with option two
where we have more data.
Yeah, cool.
That's very sane.
Go ahead.
Oh, sorry.
So use both options or put both in the pipeline.
Oh, that's interesting.
I see.
All right.
So see if option one,
let option one see if anything changed.
If something changed,
then pass this on your network.
Oh, okay.
That's cool.
That could work.
Yeah, cool.
Yeah, that could work.
So it could cascade the multiple steps.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
So how expensive is it to run this neural network
in the cloud?
So actually,
so I would usually want to design both of these
to run at the edge,
meaning on the device.
Oh, this one.
So it turns out that streaming video
is fairly expensive.
So I think,
yeah, I feel like, boy,
I don't have numbers at tip of my fingertips,
but I think running this 24-7 is not feasible.
So we definitely need something to fill it down.
But sending, you know,
I don't know,
a few images every minute
is probably not a problem.
Yeah.
Okay.
Sorry.
All right.
Sample certain times,
sample certain frames of the video
in order to get all of them.
Yes.
I guess so.
Although, yeah,
although I think if you have a video of my front door,
you need a way to sample other than random,
I guess.
Right?
Because a lot of time,
nothing happens.
Unless you take one frame per minute,
I guess,
which would be okay.
But then we don't want someone waiting there
for a full minute
before we finally get around to sampling
and then sending it.
So, yeah.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Could we use the same images
for training this network
to train this option two network?
Maybe.
I think it's actually one of those things
I would say we have to try it
before we know if it works.
It might be doable.
It depends a lot on what data we collected
to train the Breakthrough network.
Yeah.
Cool.
Anything else?
All right.
Let's take a cool last one.
Go ahead.
Cool.
Right.
Yeah.
How about use option one
and keep it really low threshold
so we send very few images.
Is that what you mean?
Yeah.
I think that'd be reasonable to try.
Well, right.
So that we don't miss too many people.
But, yeah.
Right.
Let's take one last comment.
I'll share a perspective on Hollywood.
Yeah, right.
Yes.
So one of the weaknesses of option one
is if there's a tree swaying in the background
or if you see a road
and there's a car that drives by
or if there's a busy street
and the car's driving by all the time
or the neighbor's cat comes and visits,
those will trigger this.
Right.
So those are downsides.
So let me share your perspective
on how I would approach this
and what we actually do.
So if you're the CTO of a startup
implementing this,
to me, it again comes down to speed.
Right?
And so what I would ask is
how long does it take to implement option one?
And how long does it take to implement option two?
And I think everyone made good points
about the pros and cons of these two options.
And if you're actually doing this,
the approach I would take is, you know,
just ask, what can I do really quickly
so I can then deploy it
and see whether it works
and then I'll fix it if it doesn't work.
Because I think these insights like
will tree swaying in the background affect it?
You know, it turns out that it actually does probably,
but maybe not if the wind isn't that strong
or if, right?
But it's really difficult to know
answers to questions like these
because you don't really know
until you stick on a bunch of cameras
in front of doors and see the data.
Then you can get more confident
in how well option one works.
Like, I don't know,
how often does the neighbor's cat actually come by?
And if there's a car that drives past,
are the cars usually so far away
that it doesn't matter
because the number of pixels per car is small, right?
So all of these are very empirical questions.
It's really difficult to answer.
And the fastest way to get answers
is just implement something quick and dirty
and then run it, see what goes wrong, and then fix it.
So what happens on, I'll tell you,
from the experience of a lot of face recognition teams
is because option one is so quick to implement,
this is like, I don't know,
five lines of Python or something, right?
And I don't know, get it out and write it for you.
Just get it out and write the five lines of Python for you.
So you can implement this in, you know,
20 minutes, maybe even less,
whereas this, I think, will take you at least many hours,
maybe longer to implement.
So my instinct would be the start of this.
And it turns out, having built many face recognition systems,
I'll tell you, this actually doesn't work well enough
for all the problems people raise.
And so we wind up going to this.
But implementing this also gives you insights
into where it's going wrong.
And I'll give you one example of one insight
that, you know, we and many other face recognition teams have,
which is it turns out that when you're approaching a camera
that's trying to recognize your face,
there are some frames that are going to be
really clear and in focus,
and a lot of frames are really blurry, right?
If you just look at a video,
someone walking toward the camera,
sometimes just, you know, when I'm stepping,
sometimes the velocity of my face is higher
and sometimes it's lower, right?
That's just what it is.
And so sometimes my face is in focus,
sometimes it's more blurry.
And it turns out that if you can select out
the high resolution frames
and feed that to face recognition,
you get much higher quality results, right?
So this is the kind of stuff that I assume,
you know, most people would not know about
until you work on a system like this.
But it turns out that when I was working on a system like that,
having a system to not just do VAD,
but also capture the video
and then deliberately select not just one,
but maybe five frames
to the high resolution and in focus of the person,
that actually gave a significant boost
to the accuracy of our face recognition system.
And I mentioned this as an example
of the sort of discovery that you have
only when you implement one of these systems,
maybe even implement this system.
But if you implement this system,
you see, boy, we're trying to recognize
a lot of pictures from blurry faces.
Maybe we need to do something about that, right?
So this is driving the empirical process
that may then lead you to train in your network,
both to see if there's a face,
but also to see if the picture of the face is in focus
to select out that frame for downstream processing.
Does that make sense?
And this is why you find that
for some meaningful fraction of questions I ask in class,
the thing that the speed is to do
is often the right answer,
because that obsession with speed
really lets you go in and figure out
what's in your data
and improve your system more efficiently, right?
So, right.
So, yeah, so what happens in the practice,
start with this, discover how it doesn't work,
because it doesn't actually work,
I can tell you that.
And then figure out,
but use those learnings to do this.
Yeah, so is there a sense of
what is a good classification,
accuracy of problems like these?
It's actually really difficult.
One of the common benchmarks,
you learn more about this in the third module
on the online videos as well,
is building machine learning systems is easier
if we have a reference level of performance,
like an aspirational target accuracy,
which is often human level performance.
And so it turns out that
the way you diagnose bias and variance,
which we'll talk about later in this course,
is easier if you know
what's an achievable level of accuracy.
And very often we'll use what a human expert could do
as the achievable level of accuracy.
And then in the case of face recognition,
definitely under controlled environments
were better than humans.
So definitely, actually,
the AI systems we build,
they're way better than I am
at recognizing human faces.
And I think AI systems are better than,
I want to say,
probably the vast majority of humans,
maybe all humans at this point,
that really distinguishing of two pictures
are the same.
And then it gets really difficult.
Then it actually gets more difficult
once you're even better than humans.
But those are, yeah.
But until you're as good as humans
on certain tasks,
using a human level of performance
is often a good benchmark.
And then if you're doing something
that even humans can't do well,
like it turns out,
you're recommending online books
or movies or whatever.
Humans aren't actually that good at that.
I think most of us have a hard time
recommending good movies,
even to our closest friends.
AI actually probably does it even better
than many of us do as humans.
Then those things,
it's harder to establish a baseline.
Cool.
All right.
Now, one final aspect
I want to touch on is
after deploying a model
to monitor and to maintain the model,
one thing that often happens is
you train a machine learning model,
works great, you know,
does well in your training set,
does well in your test set,
works great,
and then you deploy it,
and then unknowingly,
the world changes
and your system no longer works, right?
So we sometimes call this
data drift or concept drift,
where the distribution of data
the world gives you is different
than what you had in your training set
or concept drift,
which is with the input-output mapping,
your X and Y changes in the world
compared to your training set.
But to ground this,
if you are training a face recognition system
now in, you know, I don't know,
when it's not too cold here in California,
you get faces of a certain distribution,
but as we approach winter,
if it starts to rain more,
people are wearing scarves,
rain jackets, you know,
people look different, right?
Or maybe we approach next summer,
more people are wearing sunglasses,
then the data distribution changes.
Or if you train a system
based on data here in California,
but we then decide to deploy it,
you know, in a different country
where people dress differently
or where their appearance is different,
the world keeps on giving us different data.
And so one of the jobs of, I think,
us as machine learning engineers
is to put in place systems
that monitor the set of concept drift or data drift
and fix problems as they arise.
When you're out building machine learning systems,
I have seen a segment of AI engineers
that think their job is to do well on a test set, right?
And so I've been in a bunch of these conversations
where the machine learning person will say,
look, I did well on the test set.
My job is done.
But then a product owner,
a business owner will say,
no, your system doesn't work.
Look at all the ways it does not work.
And then if the machine learning person says,
well, that's not my problem.
I do well on the test set.
I think that's not a constructive way
to move it forward.
So I encourage you to think of yourselves
if you're building a machine learning system.
I think of my job as building something that works.
And that can be different
than building something that works on the test set.
So if ever you're working on a product
and someone says, you know,
I know you did well on the test set,
but your system doesn't work,
I would encourage you not to respond.
But my job is to do well on the test set.
I encourage you to think about
why doing well on the test set
doesn't translate to doing well
on the application that people actually care about.
And then they'll lean in and go and fix that, right?
And one of the common problems
for why doing well on the test set
doesn't translate to doing well in real life
is if the data distribution changes,
in which case you may need to update
the distribution of data you're training on
in order to capture what has changed in the world.
And just a few other examples.
I feel like, you know,
the world gives us new data all the time.
So if you're building a web search engine,
sometimes the new politician is elected,
or there's a new movement,
or some new video goes viral,
or, I don't know,
Taylor Swift releases a new album,
I don't know, whatever,
and then people are suddenly searching for a brand.
I thought I'd get a lot from that.
No, all right, no.
No Swifties here.
All right.
But then suddenly a lot of people
are searching for a brand new thing,
and so the distribution of data you get
is different because the world has changed.
Or I've done a lot of work in factories.
There's actually a reasonable chance
a cell phone you have in your pocket
may have been inspected by software
that my teams wrote.
But, you know, sometimes the materials change,
or there's a new machine installed
in the manufacturing line,
and this machine makes a new type
of scratch in the cell phone.
So data changes in inspection lines as well.
Or one thing that actually surprised me,
when I work on self-driving cars,
one of the things I was working with,
we trained a lot on data in California,
and then when we took the cars to Texas,
you and I as people, we can drive just fine
in California or in Texas,
but it turns out that traffic lights
look really different in Texas and California, right?
So it's traffic lights, horizontal, vertical.
I think part of it is there are very high winds
in some parts of Texas,
so a lot of traffic lights tend to be
strung up differently to be robust to high winds, right?
And so traffic lights actually look pretty different in Texas.
So the models we train in California,
they don't work in Texas.
We've got to get new data, refresh the data.
So a lot of that is a process of monitoring
and maintaining the model,
even when something in the world changes.
And before going on to monitoring the model performance
and maintaining it,
one interesting difference in performance
between this and this is,
option one is a very simple model, right?
It basically has one parameter, which is epsilon,
the fraction of pixels that change.
And so this, because it's so simple,
it's actually very robust to changes in distribution.
For example, say it's a hot summer
and a lot of people are wearing sunglasses.
Well, the fraction of pixels that change, right?
Even when people are wearing sunglasses,
it doesn't change that much.
Maybe if it's Halloween
and people are wearing crazy large costumes,
maybe that would change,
but this is actually a very robust algorithm
because it's so simple.
In contrast, if you train on data
with no one wearing sunglasses,
because the sun's not that hot these days, right?
Then with everyone starts to wear sunglasses,
this is actually less robust.
So one of the advantages
of very simple non machine learning based systems
is they may be less susceptible to data drift
because maybe I tuned this parameter epsilon
to a limited data set,
but even when the data changes,
this tuning can be quite robust.
But if I train a neural network
with say thousands or tens of thousands of parameters,
then I'm more likely to have overfit
to people without sunglasses.
So if people start wearing sunglasses,
you're more likely to have to update this model, right?
And if you are building a...
Sorry, right, cool, boy.
If you're building a system,
it turns out to be incredibly helpful
if you can get user permission
to stream a little bit of data
back to your cloud hosted service
so that respecting user privacy,
being careful often,
transparent privacy practices,
I think that privacy is really important, right?
So do be transparent, do the right thing for users.
And if you're able to do that
and get a little bit of data back to your cloud
to plot to dashboards,
and maybe one practice that I've seen is
when building a high stakes application,
one good practice would be to gather your team together
and get a diverse set of opinions
on all the things that could change
and all the things that could go wrong.
And I've built quite a few machine learning systems
and I found that when we sit down
and brainstorm all the things that could go wrong,
including the data distribution changes,
I don't think I have ever seen something go wrong
in real life that we did not identify as a possible problem.
I might be wrong, but at least right now
when we sat down, we really brainstormed
all things that go wrong.
I think I have yet to see something go wrong
that was not on the list of stuff that we brainstormed.
And so if you brainstorm,
and this is true for safety critical applications as well,
it turns out creative teams,
you can actually think of all sorts of things
that could change the data or things that go wrong.
And that then lets you try to design
a set of dashboards or metrics to put in place
to monitor whether or not any of the things
that you think might go wrong actually do go wrong.
So we may put in place dashboards like how often,
it turns out re-authentication is a common thing.
How often does a user need to authenticate twice
before they let through?
That's actually a sign of user frustration, right?
So let's build a dashboard to do that.
How often does a user have to try twice?
It probably means something went wrong the first time.
How often do you accept versus reject the user?
And what is the latency of the system?
And I find that just as it's difficult to know in advance
what's in your data,
it's actually difficult to know in advance
what dashboard will be the most useful.
And so the best practice I tend to recommend
is brainstorm a lot of things that go wrong,
brainstorm a lot of metrics,
and then just create very rich dashboards
where this is time latency,
time re-authentication, right?
Time, the number of zeros versus ones,
and then draw plots over time
to see how these rates trend over time.
And if you're able to have a lot of dashboards
and sample and just look at some of the data
for where you suspect you may be making a mistake,
that often is then a good way
for you to have a higher chance of spotting
when there might be a problem.
And in the times I've built large dashboards
with 20, 30 metrics,
I've found that it's surprisingly difficult
to know in advance which dashboards
would turn out to be useful.
I think in exploratory data analysis
and data science, again,
because we often don't know what's in the data
or what the data will give us in the future,
we just, frankly, plot a lot of stuff
and then go and figure out from there
what is interesting, right?
So the cost of plotting something
in a Jupyter notebook is fairly low.
So let's just plot a lot of stuff,
have a lot of dashboards,
and if you end up with 30, 50, 100 dashboards
tracking these metrics over time,
then hopefully in a few days or a few weeks,
you figure out that a lot of them are really boring.
So we figure out that, well,
latency is just not a thing
because with cloud hosted deployment,
it's just very constant.
So, well, let's get rid of that
because that's just a very boring plot.
I'm just not worried about that.
And so we often plot a lot of things
and then prune back
to then have a smaller number of metrics
that we track and monitor for the long term.
And then eventually when you get a sense of,
just being the normal range for some metric,
you can then also put in place upper and lower alarms
so that if it ever goes above or below certain bounds,
they'll trigger an alarm,
like go page someone to take a look,
to figure out if something's gone wrong.
That make sense?
And so unfortunately,
just because you train them all the time
in a real-world production setting,
it doesn't mean you're done
because you deploy it
and then the world will give you surprising data
and having a plan to monitor what happens
as well as to maintain the model,
meaning get new data, update the system
to fix problems as they arise.
That is often an important part
of the practicalities
of deploying a machine learning system as well.